<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API">
  <title>REST API</title>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This section describes the REST API provided by the Apache Qpid Broker-J. The REST API is intended
      for use by developers who wish to automate the management or monitoring of the Broker. It
      is also very useful for adhoc monitoring on the command line using tools such as
        <literal>curl</literal>.</para>
    <para>The REST API provides access to all of the Broker's entities using hierarchical paths
      expressed by the URI. Responses are returned in JSON format.</para>
    <para>The <literal>GET</literal> method request retrieves information about an object, the
        <literal>DELETE</literal> method requests the removal of one, and the <literal>PUT</literal>
      or <literal>POST</literal> methods perform updates or create new objects. The
        <literal>POST</literal> method is also used to invoke operations.</para>
    <para>The REST API is versioned with the version number embedded within the URI. The general form
      of the URI is <literal>/api/&lt;version&gt;</literal> where &lt;version&gt; is a dot separated
      major and minor model version prefixed with "v", for example, "v6.1" (without the quotation marks).
      For convenience the alias <literal>latest</literal> (<literal>/api/latest</literal>) signifies the
      latest supported version.</para>
    <para>There are also some ancillary services under URI <literal>/service</literal> used for
      authentication and logout.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-APIDocs">
    <title>REST API documentation</title>
    <para>REST API documentation is available on-line from any Broker at location
        <literal>/apidocs</literal>. It is also linked from the menu of the Web Management Console.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Authentication">
    <title>Authentication</title>
    <para>Before you can use the REST API, you must authenticate. Authentication decisions are made
      by the <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Authentication-Providers">authentication
        provider</link> associated with HTTP <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Ports">port</link>
      on which you connect.</para>
    <para>You may authenticate using <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4422.txt">SASL</link>
        (<literal>/service/sasl</literal>) or <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2617">HTTP
        Basic Authentication</link>. The latter is convienent when using tools such as
        <literal>curl</literal> on the command line. This is illustrated in the examples
      below.</para>
    <para>For SASL authentication use a <literal>GET</literal> request to
        <literal>/service/sasl</literal> to get a list of supported SASL mechanisms, and use
        <literal>PUT</literal> to the same URL to perform the SASL negotiation.</para>
    <para>It is possible to end an authenticated session using
      <literal>/service/logout</literal>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Create">
    <title>Configured Object creation</title>
    <para>Methods PUT or POST can be used to create ConfiguredObject.</para>
    <para> ConfiguredObject can be created by submitting PUT request against ConfiguredObject full
      URI (the one ending with configured object name) or by submitting PUT/POST request against
      parent URI. The request encoding should be json (application/json) and request body should
      contain attributes values in json format. On successful completion of operation a response
      should be returned having response status code set to 201 and response header "Location" set
      to ConfiguredObject full URI. If object with a such name/id already exist and POST/PUT
      requests is made against parent URI, an error response should be returned having response code
      409 (conflict) and body containing the json with the reason of operation failure. If object
      with a such name/id already exist and and PUT request is made against ConfiguredObject full
      URI, then ConfiguredObject update should be performed and http status code 200 should be
      returned. If ConfiguredObject cannot be created because of validation failure(s) the response
      should have http status code set 422 (Unprocessible Entity) and body should contain json with
      the reason of operation failure. On any other failure to create ConfiguredObject the response
      should have status code set to 400 (Bad Request) and payload should contain a json with error
      explaining the exact reason of failure. </para>
    <example>
      <title>Examples of REST calls for Queue creation</title>
      <para> To create Queue with name "my-queue" on a virtual host with name "vh" (which is
        contained within virtual host node with name "vhn") either of the following requests should
        be made: </para>
      <screen>PUT /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <screen>POST /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <screen>PUT /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <para> Response code 201 should be returned on successful queue creation. Response header
        "Location" should be set to "/api/latest/queue/test/my-queue". If queue with name "my-queue"
        already exists and either of 2 first requests above were used, an error response with
        response code 409 (conflict) and body containing json with message that queue exists should
        be returned. If queue with name "my-queue" exists and last request is used, then Queue
        update should occur. </para>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Update">
    <title>Configured Object update</title>
    <para>Methods PUT or POST can be used to update ConfiguredObject.</para>
    <para> ConfiguredObject can be updated by submitting PUT or POST request against
      ConfiguredObject full URI (the one ending with configured object name). The request encoding
      should be json (application/json) and request body should contain a ConfiguredObject json
      (with all or only modified attributes). On successful completion of operation a response code
      200 should be returned. If ConfiguredObject does not exists and PUT method is used, such
      object should be created (201 response will be returned in this case). If ConfiguredObject
      does not exists and POST method is used, an error response should be returned having response
      status code 404 and payload with json explaining the problem. If any error occur on update, a
      response with response code 400 or 422 or 404 should be sent back to the client containing
      json body with error details. </para>
    <example>
      <title>Examples of REST calls for Queue update</title>
      <para>To update Queue with name "my-queue" on a virtual host with name "vh" (contained in
        virtual host node with name "vhn") either of the following requests can be made:</para>
      <screen>POST /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <screen>POST /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue HTTP/1.1</screen>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Delete">
    <title>Configured Object deletion</title>
    <para>Method DELETE can be used to delete ConfiguredObject. Alternatively, ConfiguredObject can
      be deleted with update request having desiredState attribute set to value "DELETED". POST or
      PUT methods can be used in this case.</para>
    <para>On successful completion of operation a response code 200 should be returned.</para>
    <para>With DELETE method object ConfiguredObject in following ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>by submitting DELETE request using ConfiguredObject full URI (the one ending with
          configured object name)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>by submitting DELETE request using parent URI and providing parameters having the same
          names as children attributes, for example, id, name, etc. Multiple children can be deleted
          in a such way. Many "id" parameters can be specified in such requests. Only children with
          matching attribute values will be deleted.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <example>
      <title>Examples of REST calls for Queue deletion</title>
      <para>To delete Queue with name "my-queue" on a virtual host with name "vh" (contained in
        virtual host node with name "vhn") either of the following requests can be made:</para>
      <screen>DELETE /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <screen>DELETE /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh?name=my-queue HTTP/1.1</screen>
      <screen>DELETE /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh?id=real-queue-id HTTP/1.1</screen>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Get">
    <title>Retrieving Configured Object details</title>
    <para>Method GET is used to retrieve an object's attributes values and statistics.</para>
    <para>To retrieve a single object, use its full URI. For instance, to retrieve a single queue:</para>
    <screen>GET /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue</screen>
    <para>To retrieve all objects beneath a parent, pass the parent's URI. For instance, to retrieve
      all queues beneath the virtualhost called <literal>vh</literal>. A collection will be returned.
    </para>
    <screen>GET /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh</screen>
    <para>Request parameters (with the same name as an attribute) are used to filter the returned collection.
      For instance, to filter those queues of type <literal>standard</literal>:</para>
    <screen>GET /api/latest/queue/vhn/vh?type=standard</screen>
    <para>Additional parameters supported in GET requests:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>depth</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>To restrict the depth of hierarchy of configured objects to return in
            response</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>actuals</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If set to "true" attribute actual values are returned instead of effective</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>excludeInheritedContext</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If set to "false" the inherited context is included from the object's ancestors. Default is true.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>oversize</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the maximum length for values of over-sized attributes to trim</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>extractInitialConfig</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If set to "true", the returned json can be used as initial configuration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Operations">
    <title>Configured Object operations</title>
    <para>Method POST is used to invoke Configured Objects operations. Some operations support
      parameters. Pass parameters using a JSON request body containing a map with a map entry for
      each parameter. </para>
    <example>
      <title>Example REST call invoking the operation clear queue</title>
      <para>To clear the queue with name "my-queue" on a virtual host with name "vh".</para>
      <screen>POST api/latest/queue/vhn/vh/my-queue/clearQueue HTTP/1.1</screen>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Status-Codes">
    <title>HTTP status codes returned by REST interfaces</title>
    <table>
      <title>HTTP status codes returned by REST interfaces</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Status code</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>200</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>REST request is successfully completed. This status code can be returned by
                update, delete and get requests.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>201</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>New configured object is created. It is returned by REST PUT and POST requests
                for creation of configured objects.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>400</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>REST request cannot be performed due to errors in request. It can be returned
                from create, update and delete requests. The details of a problem are provided in
                the response payload in json format.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>401</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The request requires user authentication</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>403</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Execution of request is not allowed due to failure to authorize user
                operation.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>404</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> The requested configured object cannot be found. This status code can be
                returned from POST update requests if configured object does not exist. The reason
                for the status code is provided in the response payload in json format. </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>409</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The request can not be performed because its execution can create conflicts in
                the broker. This status code can be returned from POST/PUT create requests against
                parent URI if configured object with requested name or id already exists. The status
                code 409 can also be returned if removal or update of configured object can violate
                system integrity. The reason for the status code is provided in the response payload
                in json format. </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>422</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The request can not be performed because provided information either incomplete
                or invalid. This status code can be returned from create or update requests. The
                reason for the status code is provided in the response payload in json
                format.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-Examples">
    <title>Examples of REST requests with curl</title>
    <example>
      <title>Examples of queue creation using curl (authenticating as user admin):</title>
      <programlisting>
#create a durable queue
curl --user admin -X PUT  -d '{"durable":true}' http://localhost:8080/api/latest/queue/&lt;vhostnode name&gt;/&lt;vhostname&gt;/&lt;queuename&gt;
#create a durable priority queue
curl --user admin -X PUT  -d '{"durable":true,"type":"priority"}' http://localhost:8080/api/latest/queue/&lt;vhostnode name&gt;/&lt;vhostname&gt;/&lt;queuename&gt;
            </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para> NOTE: These curl examples utilise an unsecured HTTP transport. To use the examples it is
      first necessary enable Basic authentication for HTTP within the HTTP Management Configuration
      (it is off by default). For details see <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Management-Managing-Plugin-HTTP"/>
    </para>
  </section>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-Query-API.xml"/>

  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Management-Channel-REST-API-CORS">
    <title>Cross Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)</title>
    <para> The Broker supports Cross Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)
      to allow web management consoles other than the one embedded in the
      broker to use the REST API.  This feature must be enabled by configuring
      the CORS Allow Origins and related attributes on the
      <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Management-Managing-Plugin-HTTP"/>
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
