<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging">
  <title>Logging</title>
  <para>This section describes the flexible logging capabilities of the Apache Qpid Broker-J.</para>
  <para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Broker is capable of sending logging events to a variety of destinations including
          plain files, remote syslog daemons, and an in-memory buffer (viewable from Management).
          The system is also open for extension meaning it is possible to produce a plugin to log to
          a bespoke destination.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Logging can be dynamically configured at runtime. For instance, it is possible to
          temporarily increase the logging verbosity of the system whilst a problem is investigated
          and then revert later, all without the need to restart the Broker.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Virtualhosts can be configured to generate their own separate log, and the Broker is
          capable of generating a log either inclusive or exclusive of virtualhost events.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Logs are accessible over Management, removing the need for those operating the Broker
          to have shell level access.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>In the remainder of this section you will first find a description of the concepts used in
    the logging subsystem. Next, you find a description of the default configuration. The section
    then concludes with a in-depth description of the loggers themselves and how they may be
    configured.</para>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Concepts">
    <title>Concepts</title>

    <para>The logging subsystem uses two concepts:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>Logger</emphasis> is responsible for production of a log. The Broker
            ships a variety of loggers, for instance, a file logger, which is capable of writing a
            log file to the file system, a Syslog Logger capable of writing to a remote syslog
            daemon and console logger capable of writing to stdout or stderr.</para>
          <para>Loggers are attached at two points within the Broker Model; the Broker itself and
            the virtualhosts. Loggers attached at the Broker can capture log events for the system
            as a whole, or can exclude events related to virtualhosts.</para>
          <para>Loggers attached to a virtualhost capture log events relating to that virtualhost
            only.</para>
          <para>The Broker and virtualhosts can have zero or more Loggers. If no loggers are
            configured, no logging is generated at all.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Inclusion rules</emphasis> govern what appears within a log. Inclusion
            rules are associated with Loggers. This means it is possible for different Loggers to
            have different contents.</para>
          <para>A Logger with no inclusion rules will produce an empty log.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Default-Configuration">
    <title>Default Configuration</title>
    <para>The default configuration is designed to be suitable for use without change in small
      production environments. It has the following characteristics:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Broker generates a single log file <literal>qpid.log</literal>. This logfile is
            rolled automatically when the file reaches 100MB. A maximum history of one file is
            retained. On restart the the log will be appended to.</para>
          <para>The log contains: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>All operational logging events. See <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Appendix-Operation-Logging"/>.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Log events from Qpid itself deemed informational or
                higher.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Log events from Qpid's dependencies (such as Derby or Jetty) that are
                  deemed warning or higher.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>The default location for the log file is
              <literal>\${QPID_WORK}/log/qpid.log</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Broker also caches the last 4096 log events in a memory cache. By default, the
            memory logger logs the same things the file logger does.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>The configuration can be customised at runtime using Management. This makes it possible to
      investigate unusual conditions <emphasis>without</emphasis> the need to restart the Broker.
      For instance, you may alter the logging level so that a verbose log is produced whilst an
      investigation is in progress and revert the setting later, all without the need to restart the
      Broker.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Loggers">
    <title>Loggers</title>
    <para>Loggers are responsible for the writing of a log. The log includes log events that match a
      Logger's inclusion rules.</para>
    <para>Loggers are associated with either the Broker or a virtualhost. Virtualhost loggers write
      only log events related to that virtualhost. Broker Loggers write log events from the Broker
      as a whole. Optionally a Broker Logger can be configured to exclude log events coming from
      virtualhosts. These abilities can be usefully exploited together in managed service scenarios
      to produce separate logs for separate user groups.</para>
    <para>Loggers can be added or removed at runtime, without restarting the Broker. However changes
      to a Logger's configuration such as filenames and rolling options don't take effect until the
      next restart. Changes to a Logger's inclusion rules take effect immediately.</para>
    <para>All loggers allow the log event layout to be customised. Loggers understand <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://logback.qos.ch/manual/layouts.html#ClassicPatternLayout"> Logback Classic
        Pattern Layouts</link>. </para>
    <para>The following sections describes each Logger implementation in detail.</para>
    <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Loggers-FileLogger">
      <title>FileLogger</title>
      <para>A <emphasis>FileLogger</emphasis> - writes a log file to the filesystem. The name and
        location of the log file, the rolling configuration, and compression options can be
        configured.</para>
      <para>The <emphasis>roll daily</emphasis> option, if enabled, will cause the log file will be
        rolled at midnight local time. The rolled over file will have a suffix in the form
          <literal>yyyy-mm-dd</literal>. In roll daily mode, <emphasis>maximum number of rolled
          files</emphasis> controls the maximum number of <emphasis>days</emphasis> to be retained.
        Older files will be deleted.</para>
      <para>The <emphasis>maximum file size</emphasis> option limits the size of any one log file.
        Once a log file reaches the given size, it will be rolled. The rolled over file will have
        the numeric suffix, beginning at <literal>1</literal>. If the log file rolls again, first
        the existing file with the suffix <literal>.1</literal> is renamed to <literal>.2</literal>
        and so forth. If roll daily is not in use, <emphasis>maximum number of rolled
          files</emphasis> governs the number of rolled <emphasis>files</emphasis> that will be
        retained.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Roll on restart</emphasis> governs whether the log file is rolled when the
        Broker is restarted. If not ticked, the Broker will append to the existing log file until it
        needs to be rolled.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Loggers-ConsoleLogger">
      <title>ConsoleLogger</title>
      <para><emphasis>ConsoleLogger</emphasis> - writes a log file standard out or standard
        error.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Loggers-SyslogLogger">
      <title>SyslogLogger</title>
      <para><emphasis>SyslogLogger</emphasis> - writes a log file to a syslog daemon using the
          <literal>USER</literal> facility. The hostname and port number of the syslog daemon can be
        configured.</para>
      <para>Log entries can be prefixed with a string. This string defaults to include the word
          <literal>Qpid</literal> and the name of the Broker or virtualhost. This serves to
        distinguish the logging generated by this Qpid instance, from other Qpid instances, or other
        applications using the <literal>USER</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Loggers-MemoryLogger">
      <title>MemoryLogger</title>
      <para><emphasis>MemoryLogger</emphasis> - writes a log file to a circular in-memory buffer. By
        default the circular buffer holds the last 4096 log events. The contents of the buffer can
        be viewed via Management. See <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Management-MemoryLogger"/></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-InclusionRules">
    <title>Inclusion Rules</title>
    <para>A <emphasis>Logger</emphasis> has one or more <emphasis>inclusion rules</emphasis>. These
      govern what appears in the log. A Logger with no inclusion rules will log nothing.</para>
    <para>Inclusion rules can be added, removed or changed at runtime. Changes take place
      immediately.</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis>Name And Level</emphasis> inclusion rule accepts log events that match
            a given <emphasis>log event source name</emphasis> and have a level that equals or
            exceeds the specified value.</para>
          <para>The log event source name refers to the fully qualified class name from which the
            event originates. These names permit a trailing wild card <literal>.*</literal>. For
            instance a source name of <literal>org.apache.qpid.*</literal> will match all events
            from classes in the package <literal>org.apache.qpid</literal> and any sub packages
            beneath.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis>Level</emphasis> governs the level of the events that will be included
            in the log. It may take one of the following values: ERROR, WARN, INFO, DEBUG, TRACE
            where ERROR is considered the highest and TRACE the lowest. In addition, there are two
            special values: OFF and ALL, the former excludes all log events whereas the latter will
            include everything. When considering whether a logging event should be included in the
            log, the logging event must have a level that matches that of the inclusion rule or be
            higher, otherwise the log event will not appear in the log.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Management">
    <title>Logging Management</title>
    <para>The logging subsystem can be completely managed from the Web Management Console or the
      REST API. You can: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Add, remove, or change the configuration of Loggers.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Add, remove, or change the Inclusion Rules.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>For FileLoggers, download the log file and rolled log files associated with
            the Logger.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>For MemoryLoggers, view the last <literal>n</literal> log
          events</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para> The figure that follows shows a FileLogger. The attributes area shows the configuration
      of the Logger. The inclusion rule table shows the rules that are associated with the Logger.
      The area towards the bottom of the tab allows the log files to be downloaded to the browser.
        <figure xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Management-FileLogger">
        <title>Viewing a file logger</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Management-Web-Logging-FileLogger.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="900px"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Viewing a file logger</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para> The figure below shows the editing of the level of an inclusion rule. <figure xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Management-InclusionRule">
        <title>Editing an inclusion rule</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Management-Web-Logging-InclusionRule.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="900px"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Editing an inclusion rule</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para> The figure below shows a Memory Logger. Note that the Memory Logger provides access to
      the cached message via the viewer towards the bottom on the tab. <figure xml:id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Logging-Management-MemoryLogger">
        <title>Viewing a memory logger</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Management-Web-Logging-MemoryLogger.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="900px"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Viewing a memory logger</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
